Welcome back.
Let's discuss what the project
closure process means for you,
the project manager.
For a project manager, it's important
to close the project properly for
a number of reasons.
Closing provides an opportunity
to reflect on how you and
your team performed, ensure
every task is completed, and
prevent confusion around
the project in the future.
I'll detail the importance of
these closing practices, as well as
the necessary documentation to
successfully close a project.
One of the most important aspects
of thoroughly closing a project is
the project closeout report.
A project closeout report is a document
created by project managers for
project managers. A project closeout
report serves three major purposes.
First, it's a blueprint to
document what the team did,
how they did it, and what they delivered.
Second, it provides an evaluation
of the quality of work. And third,
it evaluates the project's performance
with respect to budget and schedule.
Similar to the retrospective, the project
closeout report can be used to determine
best practices when it
comes to future projects.
Think of it as a transfer of knowledge
from you to future project managers.
For instance, once a project closes,
there's a chance a similar project or
a continuation of that project will
come up within the organization,
and maybe a different
project manager is assigned
to this new project while
you go on to other things.
If you create an in-depth closeout report,
it will help the newly-assigned
project manager immensely to know what
happened previously on a similar project.
Your closeout report could include
things that worked out well and
things that didn't work out so well.
Creating a closeout report will also
reduce the time you spend answering
questions as the new project
manager gets up to speed.
It's safe to assume that the people
reading your report in the future will be
unfamiliar with the project,
so be as detailed as possible.
That way the new project team will be able
to form an understanding of the purpose,
execution, and outcome of the project
based on your report alone.
In your project closeout report, you'll
want to include the following things:
An executive summary:
this means a description of the process
and what the purpose of the project was.
This should be short and concise;
a few sentences to a paragraph, maximum.
If an executive did not have time
to read the entire document and
only had time to read this executive
summary, would they be able to understand
the project highlights? A list of key
accomplishments: think of this as a way to
highlight the team's accomplishments, as
well as the overall impact of the project.
Include any lessons learned,
like: what went well, and why?
What went wrong, and why?
What were the major effects of key
problem areas, such as scope creep and
schedule slip?
Any open items: this could be things
you didn't quite get to or ideas for
changes you'd make if
you'd had the time.
Your next steps: things like, are there
expected follow up projects, and
is there any ongoing maintenance required?
You also want to include important
information about the schedule and
important deadlines, like: what were your
milestones, and how did you choose them?
How long did the project take?
Did the project stay on track? And
any information about major setbacks.
Be sure to list resources and
team members. Explain who is involved and
what their roles were.
This is also a key way to acknowledge
people who contributed to the project's
completion. And finally, include
a resources and project archive section.
This will include links to things
like your original project plan,
any documented stakeholder communication
and feedback (like meeting notes),
and documentation used to track,
monitor, and report,
and any technical information related
to the project deliverables like user
guides and manuals.
Hopefully by now, you understand how
project closeout reports are beneficial to
not only the organization, but
the project manager as well.
Project closeout reports promote
visibility among team members and
create more efficient future projects.
All right, we've covered a lot
of information. Great job for
sticking with it!
In the next video,
we'll revisit the concepts you've
learned as we recap the module.